welcome to the hard based medicine
inspirations podcast
with professor dr yann bonifa and daniel
schmachtenberger
thank you daniel thank you for being
with us today
thanks for putting this together we had
a chance today to talk about
heart-based medicine during the board
meeting and during the opening ceremony
and i just wonder what does heart-based
medicine
look like for you if you were to
describe it in your own terms
now the first
kind of sense that i have is that
people are called to a life path in the
healing professions because of
a care for the quality of experience of
other people
and the actual sacredness
of human life and human experience and
wanting to be in service to and devotion
to that
so heart-based medicine would be where
the
entire system of medicine and all of the
interactions
were designed from and in service to
that devotion and that sacredness
so heart based medicine is about a
sacred space for you
yeah i mean we think about medicine
being
preventing and correcting illness and
promoting health
people's experience of life and what
they can do with their life
to affect the experience of others is
sacred so then medicine is
what is in service to their capacity to
experience life fully and contribute to
life fully
beautiful in many ways this is where
medicine is coming from at least in our
part of the world in our cultures that
medicine was very much in the domain of
the religious missions
and that was the understanding of health
care that was the understanding of care
given
and of elevating the potential of of the
ones we serve
is this something very specific to to
our cultures
or is this something that you see as a
like as a principle
beyond the kind of cultural and
religious backgrounds that we share
in western europe i think this might be
as
unifying a thing across cultures as
there is in terms of
medicine women and medicine men and
shamans
and chinese medicine and ayurvedic
medicine led
early humans figuring out how do we care
for each other how do we
care for ourselves how do we prevent
illness how do we fix illness
um
obviously the whole focus to do that
would be not just self-preservation but
also care for each other so
i think that's probably as unifying a
thing as there is
yeah so care is the unifying principle
so it cares the unifying principle and
we
see that all the talk in healthcare
about the importance of care and we see
how
it is delivered
what do you see as the current
the strongest obstacles i feel like
those those elements in our current
healthcare
system in the way that we go about
healthcare what do you see as the
current obstacles
to deliver the kind of care that we
would perceive as
a secret
a lot actually
i'm i'm happy to unpack this but there's
a lot of systemic factors
um there's obviously trillions of
dollars flowing through the thing we
call
global health care industrial complex or
at large and pharmaceuticals and
hospitals and
industries and insurance industries
there's also all of the money in the
world flowing through
things that affect health when we look
at
the burning of coal and oil and what
that does to the environment that then
we're embedded in and breathing and
drinking the water from when we
look at agriculture that depletes the
topsoil or sprays glyphosate on all the
food
like upstream from someone being sick
and coming to the hospital is do we
actually have a civilization that's
promoting health
and how many places do we have a
civilization that through
structures that create ubiquitous
psychological stress
and structures that actually again
expose us to
ubiquitous pollution and poor forms of
nutrition
when you just think about that like the
the goal of almost every business is to
maximize the lifetime revenue of the
customer
and nothing does that better than
addiction obviously the the supply side
might be a multi-billion dollar company
relative to an individual consumer and
so there's a
kind of asymmetric warfare in terms of
their capacity to
influence with commercial media you know
so many things
so if we wanted a society that was
promoting maximum health we would want
to be
minimizing addiction everywhere which
would mean that
any place where addiction was profitable
we would have a fundamental
conflict we'd have a perverse incentive
in the nature of
that type of market dynamic so
you know i think there's a huge amount
of perverse incentive
that's one place where there are
structural issues
i think that there are places where
out of caution because of malpractice
and whatever else
hospitals create policies there are
insurance guidelines that actually don't
allow doctors to do things that would
demonstrate certain kinds of care
i think that we have
a medical school system where the
average amount of nutrition that is
taught
to a medical doctor is extraordinarily
low relative to the importance of
nutrition and health
but similarly how much psychology
should actually be taught so that the
doctor can actually really understand
the experience of the patient well and
be able to relate and
work through that should be a much
bigger percentage of the training
that occurs i think we also have a
situation where
you can't actually measure the felt
sense of love and care in the same way
that you can measure
cholesterol and blood pressure and so
you end up optimizing for the things
that you measure
i think mri machines are expensive and
they're important
so you make big hospitals that a lot of
people go to as opposed to small county
clinics
and because there's economies of scale
but i think the economies of scale mean
you don't really know your doctor your
doctor doesn't know you you're one of
maybe hundreds or thousands of people
that they're going to see
and so i think again the economies of
scale
end up really damaging personal
connection and personal rapport
i think the most important diagnostic
tool there is
is really detailed medical intake
and really having the time to think
through and pay attention
and then a continuity of being able to
think about that for
the patient and there's just that
requires a certain amount of
time being allocated so i think there's
a lot
of structural factors that are oriented
to things like
lowering liability and maximizing profit
and economies of scale all of which are
not optimized for
what supposedly the whole thing is in
service to
hmm thank you that makes a lot of sense
can resonate very much with the
importance of
intake that is based on a deep listening
really being present with the patient
understanding where they're coming from
and seeing their disease through their
eyes
where you're talking about you're
touching on many issues but you're also
touching on one of the points you're
raising
is that the person's subjective
experience of their disease
and how they feel and what it means to
their lives
is something that is worth exploring and
yet it is hard to measure
so the measures that we currently have
available
are
are they too crude or are they just is
it just
structurally impossible to measure the
subjective experience
well by by definition it is structurally
impossible to measure
subjective experience a measurement
means some needle move means it's in the
domain of the objective or third person
i can measure a neural correlate
i can measure a endocrine correlate
otherwise i have to actually listen to
the person report their own experience
then of course we're going to have all
the biases that self-reporting has
and someone having reasons they don't
want to say how miserable they are or
they want to exaggerate it for empathy
or
they have a limited vocabulary to
express it
um
so i do think that there is a need for a
lot of question asking of things that
cannot be
measured in blood tests so how do we
deal with this approach so we
we know that when we talk to patients
that we find out things and as you say
there are biases so there's there are
preferences there's recall
there's you know there's all sorts of
things that affect this and
and a lot of the approaches that we take
in in everyday
routine clinics is trying to bring some
insert some objectivity
into this assessment seeing to what
degree can we rely on this
but in a way what we do is we take our
tests that we apply our observations
of that person that we call objective
observations
we take those as the reference point and
whatever the patient says
is measured against that yet when i hear
you correctly
then what we really want to do is we
want to improve on understanding
the subjective experience better
okay so there's there's a number of
parts we can look at here
there's the way that someone's
subjective experience
affects their objective physiology right
so the whole domain of
psychoneuroimmunology and the way that
stress affects health and the way that
better psychological disposition placebo
dynamics et cetera effect health
so we want to actually be able to work
with people's
subjective experience as part of
medicine that's one thing
the other thing is that some people
might have a disease that can't be cured
and actually still have a good
subjective experience of life based on
their focus and their meaning making
versus having a totally ruined
experience of life so subjective
experience is
a terminal value in and of itself it so
it is both useful for
supporting objective physiologic health
and
it is intrinsically valuable independent
of physiologic health um there's a bunch
of other reasons to
talk to a patient and ask them questions
though um
you and i were talking before that
modern allopathic medicine does a really
good job in places where we actually
understand the causation clearly
and generally that tends to be more in
the direction of things that were acute
like an acute injury it's pretty clear
like oh
there was a puncture wound we're gonna
sew up the puncture wound or
there was an acute infection and we can
see what type of infection it is maybe
an antibiotic can treat it or there was
a
acute poisoning and we're going to do an
acute kind of detox but there was a
acute incident and then immediate
symptomology and we can trace causation
but with autoimmune disease and with
cognitive decline and neurodegenerative
disease
and psychiatric disease and cancer
that's not the case and so for the most
part we don't actually know why those
things are happening
and it happens to be my
uh belief similar to much of the kind of
functional medicine and naturopathic
world
that most of those diseases are
multifactorial they don't have one cause
they have a lot of causes and it's not
the same set of causes
every time so there actually isn't one
thing called rheumatoid arthritis or one
thing called ms
from a pathoideology point of view
there's a system that's being exposed to
things that don't create immediate
symptomology
but that are dysregulating homeodynamics
and those dysregulated homeodynamics
make one more susceptible to the
additional stressors dysregulating
homeodynamics
more until eventually we cross a
threshold and now we get symptomology
and biomarkers
and a cluster of symptomology and
biomarkers gets a disease name
and but if if i really start paying
attention to those things and
wanting to be able to trace a complex
causal situation that's multifactorial
and maybe very delayed causation in time
then i want a totally different kind of
intake
right i might want to be asking really
detailed questions to see when they've
ever been exposed to mold
or when they were ever exposed to
industrial chemicals or they spend a lot
of time with epoxy at a certain point or
whatever it is or when they had third
world travels where they
got nasty infections and what symptoms
so i want a timeline of when
different symptoms kicked on and a
timeline of different kinds of stresses
and exposures when there was a
micro-traumatic brain injury that didn't
show up in an mri but it doesn't mean
that there actually wasn't a micro tbi
that affected functional patterning in
the brain
and if i'm able to
look at the current symptomology the
current labs
the progression of symptomology and the
progression of exposures and have all of
that fit together and make sense
then i might be informed as to how to
start a treatment that is actually
addressing
more than just symptomology and you know
disease manifestation
and there's no way i'm going to get that
without asking them a lot of questions
yeah
so so is there do you do you feel that
this is
this is an area of research that is
developing
i mean i think that the
environmental medicine functional
medicine naturopathic medicine
communities have been focused on with
chronic complex illness in particular
where
the best modern treatments are mostly
symptomatic
um you know and not not just symptomatic
a biologic
can actually decrease the
total tissue damage from a connective
tissue disorder
and obviously if we're cutting a cancer
out or radiating it out or poisoning it
out
it's still better than leaving it there
oftentimes but
why was there increased carcinogenesis
in the first place
and why did the body's immune system not
deal with the carcinogenesis are still
upline questions especially if we don't
want this person to get cancer again
and especially if the things that might
have led to it might be signs of
underlying dysregulation that affect
other
um things i think there is a
increasing awareness that chronic
complex illness is not just stupid
bodies
um it is just a kind of deeper
complexity where it's not
one disease one cause and we're going to
have one pill it is
radically complex regulatory systems
many different
elements of causation that end up
leading to
things that present like a cluster of
symptoms and biomarkers that we call a
disease
that is very fascinating as i think in
most of the
research that we see published today
most of the clinical research is listed
that we see published today what i
observe is that the
the schematic the methodology is very
much the same so we kind of have two or
two points of observation
and between the two points of
observation we assume a linear
correlation
but what we don't look at are you if you
look at the classic table one in a
publication where
we're looking at the demographics
comparing the two groups
you know three or four or five different
variables so we're looking at you know
is
you know gender ethnicity age
so like really really crude variables
and at the end everybody feels
comfortable that both groups are
comparable
well what we're not looking at at all is
what happens before
the trial what are these life stories
what is this
what is this the the complex
of um homeodynamic regulatory systems
interacting with each other and and
building up in a way that that we have
great difficulties to understand that we
certainly don't have any
measures or markers for this
when we establish these let's say if we
get better at asking
questions and really getting at least a
reported picture of what happened
do you feel that the if we basically
exploded the number of variables from
you know age and sex and ethnicity to to
maybe let's say
200 or 500 variables so if we were
compiling this of
of measures or indicators
would we really learn more about what
happened before
an event um
yeah so
what are the right methods to gain the
kinds of insights we want in a domain as
complex as human physiology
is a very interesting question if we
look at a clinical trial
say for drug research that's trying to
see does this drug do something
beyond the placebo
we're going to get something like a
gaussian distribution
where all we you know it's going to work
pretty well for some people
and it's going to work not well for
other people and there will be some
range of effect for a lot of people we
just want to see that that some
range of effect and maybe the front of
the bell curve is better than what a
placebo is
but why it works really well for these
people and not really well for these
people or maybe even really badly for
these people is a bunch of other
variables that are just hidden under the
shape of a bell curve
and so obviously we would like to find
that out so
that doesn't mean that that is a
worthless study that's an interesting
study
but it it if we go
all the way to the other end we get
how can we get as much information about
this one person as possible rather than
this one drug across all people right
how can i get as much information about
this person
and now we're starting to do n equals
one kinds of studies and optimization
so i totally think there are places for
clinical trials of course
if we have more metrics if they're
appropriate metrics
additional insight comes because not
just are you likely to be able to see
more things but you also start to get to
see what are the relationships between
these metrics and
are there combinatorial insights
but as soon as i realized that i'm not
just looking at a genome i'm looking at
the combinatorics
on all of the polymorphisms possible on
all of the
the genes and then all the combinatorics
on the epigenome
and then the proteome recursively
changing it we're never going to be able
to compute all that
it is actually not computable
so there are better ways we have to
think about
how do we actually understand what
health is and if we think about
health as the integrity of the
regulatory systems
so the homeodynamics of how the body
self-organizes and self-regulates
and the homeodynamic not just the
homeodynamic state
but the homeodynamic capacity right like
typically most of the
studies that most the tests we do in
medicine are testing state
so we're testing cholesterol level or
we're testing blood sugar or
whatever it is but what's really going
to determine the overall
health is much more related to under
some kind of
stress how does the body maintain being
within a homeodynamic range so
you know we do this sometimes with a
glucose stress test or with a
stress echocardiogram and those are
super insightful but there's a lot of
things we don't do those with where
it might be in range but very fragile
and could come out of range easily which
means
that the person doesn't have a disease
but they're very susceptible
and so yet if i see very high
homeodynamic capacity across lots of
axes
that's a measure of the robustness of
health
so yeah different types of interesting
diagnostics in the future
thank you so when we are
so what i hear from you is
assuming linear
uni causal association is
is a degree of simplification that silly
is really not very helpful
um i mean for some things
in the knife wound case it's fine yeah
except we
need to ask you know
are they clumsy or are they getting in
knife fights for dumb reasons so there
might be something upstream
but so for some things unicausal is fine
but for most anything that emerged not
immediately following an obvious
causation event
this is why we don't actually have real
cures we have symptomatic treatments and
you know ameliorative treatments for
most complex chronic disease
so the etiology of disease
we will more likely find answers for
what is the real cause of disease
if we look at non-linear models and we
look at
the the period before the dis ease
started before the symptoms occur and
see what what are the different factors
that have built up and reached that
threshold
when you
speculate about what might be the areas
that affect the human body
what are the areas that if they stack up
will lead to an imbalance of
dysregulation that becomes symptomatic
yeah what do you believe are those areas
you know there's some actual
pretty simple models we can start to
look at this comprehensively through so
i mean chinese medicine and ayurvedic
medicine
actually had some kind of good holistic
heuristics to start with even though
they didn't have all the
assessments we have like say you take a
roughly chinese medicine point of view
of where is there too much of something
or is there not enough of something so
toxicity and deficiency this is pretty
good
starting model for uh predispositions
towards disease
so uh you can think about that we
evolved to be able to like our
our genetics evolved to have a certain
set of behaviors
interacting with a certain set of
environmental
parameters so where our
behaviors are very different than kind
of what we evolved to
handle or where our environment is
meaningfully different
those are going to be interesting things
to look at so
you know too much well too much can look
like things that we shouldn't have any
amount of like
glyphosate and pesticides and you know
and we're really kind of ubiquitously
exposed
to the volatile organic compounds coming
out of this carpet and out of the paint
right there's we have built a world that
we're actually not genetically fit for
um where there are externalities to our
health of the ways that we do lots of
things
and so when you look at all the volatile
organic compounds or all of the you know
petrochemicals that are in the
environment
most of them are either endocrine
disruptors or neurotoxins or carcinogens
so then we look at how many diseases fit
into those being part of the underlying
ideology right
so too much of things that shouldn't
have really been there at all
and but obviously too much sugar
um or you know
there can be excesses of certain
nutrients in relationship to
other nutrients like zinc copper balance
or
calcium magnesium balance or things like
that
um obviously we're not just limited to
talking about
uh environmental toxins that aren't
alive we can also talk about things that
are alive so infection would be kind of
a subclass of
too much of something and that can
either be things that
should be there but they're overgrown
like sibo and other kinds of microbiome
disorders or actual infections but
pathogens that are not
normally part of our healthy kind of
microbiome
and this is where the concept of a
subclinical infection or a subclinical
toxicity is important
which is let's say that i have a level
of mercury exposure
or a level of lead exposure where we're
going to say oh yes i have lead
poisoning well lead poisoning is at this
threshold but the ideal amount of lead
that i would have would be
down here well there's a whole level in
here which is i don't yet have the level
that we would diagnose with acute lead
poisoning
that is more than none it has some
effect
and that also ends up being true with
infections that are not necessarily
showing up as acute infection
but are testable and that have effect so
we see helicobacter pylori in the
stomach
being able to cause ulcers and cause
stomach cancer over a very long time
period
or h pv and cervical cancer or throat
cancer things like that
for those few that we've found recently
it's pretty safe to assume that there's
lots more like that where the
correlations are just not as clear yet
and that's one of the things that again
some of the
infectious study and environmental
toxicology studies that functional
medicine is doing i think are really
interesting
um so too much of
various things not enough of and
obviously we can look at things like
not enough exercise not enough sleep not
enough
human contact the none of human contact
is actually
profound because
that ends up being one of the most
profound
drivers of addiction which is then going
to cause so many other health
issues but also not enough of specific
nutrients
and we see that we have a
you know modern american diet
or modern industrial world diet is very
high in macronutrients and often
low in really critical micronutrients
and
longevity is usually best optimized by
lower macronutrients and higher
micronutrients which is closer to what
evolutionary environments would have
so that's like a starting framework
thank you
so here you have identified areas or
risk factors
and if they're compiling they might add
so these are the areas that we would
like to explore further and more deeply
in in an intake as you described it
where we ask lots of questions and try
to understand what happened
before the patient has reached a stage
of disease
yeah when we don't have a lot of time
when talking to the patients and you
mentioned the the systemic factors the
limiting
factors of how we are setting up our
healthcare system certainly i i feel
that limited time is a critical factor
we need to make choices we need to make
choices about what questions to ask
and one way is to go through a protocol
one way is to go through a long list of
questions and kind of ask all the
possible questions
and then i hope that either ourselves or
some computer will be able to make sense
of it
and then there's another way to make
choices
and that depends it involves the
observer
it involves the healthcare provider so
it involves the way we show up as a
healthcare provider we relate to the
patient and we ask these questions
we briefly touched on the subjective
experience of the disease
and you talk you touched on
homeodynamics
as as the key principle to understand
behind disease evolution
now if we see that you're a homodynamic
system and i'm a homeodynamic system
is there a way that those two systems
can come into resonance
is there a way that i can tune my system
into yours and by doing so
i can actually ask the right questions
i would ask you as a clinician have you
had this experience
yeah that's what it seems like
i don't think we have to get hung up on
wondering what the mechanism of
intuition is to acknowledge
that there's a reality to it
is it some electromagnetic resonance
that's happening
maybe that's a cool idea is it simply
that i have a lot of experience and when
i take the time to
quiet i process the information in my
own internal
neurologic database better that's a fine
idea too
i don't really i don't i actually don't
want to attach to
a mechanistic explanation of how
intuition works that someone can
say not well enough verified and reject
to say that increasing awareness
and presence and perceptivity is
valuable
and it will lead to better insights from
wherever that comes
about what's going on with the patient
and how to ask
the right questions
that's interesting so you're leaving
care as a sacred
space and you're leaving intuition
as a sacred space so
it feels like we need to talk about love
in a way connecting the two at least
that's what it feels like to me
here's another sacred space and another
question of can we
measure or should we measure what might
be the value of measuring
how we relate and
and how we describe the phenomenon
of love or resonance
we talked about this earlier
we can't measure love
we can measure things going on with the
physiology
when we say that we're feeling something
that we call love
that maybe statistically correlate to
some degree
and whether i'm measuring oxytocin and
other kind of neural hormones and
neurotransmitters or i'm measuring heart
rate variability or measuring
some kind of eeg coherence pattern
those aren't useless things to do like
that's interesting
but i could just say
pick the right person to marry on paper
whether you have any feelings for them
or not and just snort oxytocin regularly
because love is just oxytocin
and most people don't resonate with that
or or
you know do a particular kind of
transcranial magnetic stimulation to the
brain region that we identified as where
love is
happening and there it is um
when a parent wakes up who is sick and
who hasn't slept in a long time who has
an infant who's worn out as can be to
take care of their infant
love is motivating them but they might
feel
like in the moment and love doesn't
really feel like a subjective emotion
it's actually something deeper than
emotion it's transcendent to emotion it
can move them even through emotion
and we might not see a
you know the particular great heart rate
variability in that moment or
whatever it is um so
i think it's interesting to study
correlation
between physiology and subjective states
but i think
if we're studying it through the method
of science and we can do a lot more
with the objective within the method of
science because that's what we study
things that are measurable
and repeatable and experience subjective
experience is not immeasurable nor
repeatable
then the temptation is going to be to
reduce subjectivity to being an
epiphenomena of objectivity
and in doing so then consciousness is
illusory and choice is illusory
or their consciousness is real as an
epiphenomena but choice is illusory
because
everything that happens in the brain is
controlled by particle physics of the
voltage differentials of sodium ions
that's the exact opposite of heart based
anything right like that is kind of
maximum
reductionism and it's not even
epistemically well-founded it's a
category error of seeing that there is
some pretty low degree of information
theoretic correlation between objective
and subjective pretending that it's
perfect
and then pretending that this is the
epiphenomenon of this one because this
is the one that we know how to actually
make causal sense of
um do i think it's important
to have some way of noticing how the
doctor and how the nurse and how the
practitioners
feel before they're with patients
and they're paying attention to how the
patients are feeling and they're paying
attention to the quality of the
relationship
totally i don't think you can measure
that
i think you can pay attention to it i
think
that you might have some indices that
are worth noticing
but there will be meaningful things that
can't be brought into an index and the
moment you do
you're actually collapsing something
very information rich to something very
not information rich and you're losing
so much information in the process
that if if you make your decisions as a
hospital or an insurance company or a
doctor based off the thing that lost all
the information
and then you normalize this is the thing
we want to do we mess it up
it's beautiful so so basically our our
attempt to
simplify questions so that we feel
comfortable to answer them
so this reductionist approach
limits our ability to see just by by the
fact that we're setting targets
to see them yeah
the dow that is nameable is not the
eternal dial
so
ultimately good medicine is not
purely algorithmic and our job
is not just to try and be robots that
just
get data that we just haven't got good
enough robots to do yet but will be
replaced by them and then
do if this than that
programs it's actually not that that's
not the job that's a
part of the job but that's definitely
not the
whole totality of the job so there is
something to
what medicine is that is trans
algorithmic
and so then you have to say well if
we're going to be training
doctors and if we're going to be
evaluating them based on a set of
metrics and the scorecard so then they
are
going to try and perform to the
scorecard they're going to mess up the
actual thing
this is what the note this is how i
interpret what the no false idols thing
is about
right is that that that
kind of graven image of that set of
metrics isn't actually the thing that
it's pointing at
it's not worthless to pay attention to
those things but you actually have to
have your choice making
be bound to the actual reality not the
information-reduced model
that's very interesting particularly
when we think of artificial intelligence
entering the space of medicine
so when we look at now there are
computers being built that
are exhibiting some features
that we would describe as compassionate
for example non-just mental listening
so some of the robots are now able to
listen
to a human being and
in a way that they there is a feedback
to the one that that is that is talking
but is non-judgmental
this this is um there's a conflation of
ideas in here
to say non-judgmental assumes a binary
with
judgmental that we're derived
we're correlating our experience of a
human that is judgmental or
non-judgmental
that computer is not being
non-judgmental nor judgmental there's
actually no one home
there is no quality it is doing an if
this than that kind of program
and even if it's doing a deep learning
program it is
simply a fully causal input output
through some set of program dynamic so
it's not really fair to call that
non-judgmental
it is doing a function he's doing what
it's told
and the the interesting observation is
is that
when um people with certain disease
conditions for example autistic
people are interacting with
these computers there seems to be a
level of
trust or acceptance that evolves
and that those
patients exhibiting features that we
would describe as autistic disease
spectrum
will reduce and they will be able to
open up and actually start a
conversation
i think that that is a statement of how
shitty the parenting is
and how shitty the doctors nurses and
educators are that the person does
better with a robot
like a fairly low-level robot rather
than it is something exciting about ai
for me um if someone's doing better with
a robot because it
simply doesn't seem judgmental and it
takes a little space even though it
doesn't love you or care about you
like that's just a really low bar i'd
rather the person have a dog
to spend time with the thing i'm excited
about
with ai in the medicine space and it's
it's confusing to even call a
machine learning do we want to
have machine learning run big data sets
to find correlations that we can't
currently find of course that's awesome
do we want to like scan all the medical
in you know
medical records in using image
recognition and run massive big data so
that we can see
early disease indicators we don't
currently know that's awesome
um
insofar as and
and of course we should be augmenting
just like we augment human memory with
books and computers we should augment
human
computational process with computational
process
so the ability to take a picture of
something and have image recognition be
able to do better
diagnosis of skin is like all of that's
great
and that actually allows as that gets
better it allows the doctors to
be less focused on just memory and
computation and more focused on actual
connection
to them know how to use that system and
to relate to the person
but there's still going to be a pretty
big gap between the doctor relating with
the person using the system
and the system acting on the person
[Music]
directly
so you now you know
[Music]
juxtaposing the human experience and
the development of machine learning or
the availability of machine learning
capacity
and we can run this on databases as you
say but we can also turn them into
we can we can inform
objects that we call robots with
machine learning abilities so they're
able to provide
services so what we're seeing is that
increasingly now there are kind of
robots evolving
that are involved in what we typically
would cause
called services of care so for example
they would help
in in household activities they would
help in
you know basic getting dressed washing
ourselves very basic
day-to-day activities and
they are helpful for people who have
um incapacity are somehow
don't have the capacity to perform
certain activities
but they're fundamentally different to a
nurse
coming to the home and actually being
with this person and providing that
support
yeah there's something about the
development of these technologies that
is awesome and liberating and helpful
and there's something about the way we
are relating to it that is gruesome
and it's important to understand both in
so far
as we're talking about a robotic
exoskeleton that can allow a paralyzed
person to
walk it's just a better wheelchair like
i mean it's just an extension of the
tooling we've already been using
um you're wearing eyeglasses that's a
tool
that helps you you're a cyborg to some
degree um
if we had ones that could autofocus and
do cool stuff like
okay that's fine
but
something that does not actually have
the capacity to care about you
replacing a dynamic where care used to
occur is tragic
now if it's simply helping you get some
stuff done you couldn't otherwise and
hopefully that increases your capacity
for authentic human interaction awesome
that the tendency of hyper
individualization
that the modern world has had modern
west in particular has had
every time you see a mass shooter who
shoots up a bunch of people at school or
somewhere
almost all of the time when the news
goes and checks the neighbors say
yeah he was super quiet he kept to
himself nobody ever saw
because in a setting where you have a
family or an extended family or a
village where humans evolve for most of
human history if you're
before you would go kill a bunch of
people you're obviously not happy
and if you're interacting with other
people to get your needs met other
people see that
they'll actually be responding and
keeping that psychopathology from
progressing that far
but if someone can be a shut-in and they
can
hardly ever interact with anyone and
maybe get an amazon drone delivery to
their house so they actually never have
to interact with anyone now they can
have some robotic care agents they can
progress in psychopathology both
in ways that make them dangerous to
society and in ways that just allow them
to be suffering
gruesomely for a long time humans
our social primates we evolved in social
environments
we have a world that totally is getting
this wrong right now
and we
we have to turn that thing around for
their
not just to like have an optimal world
i actually don't think we have any
chance of having a world continue at all
from the point of view of existential
catastrophic risk if we don't solve this
particular
thing because say someone is progressing
in psychopathology and they're really
upset
and the best technology for killing they
have is a knife they're just not going
to hurt that many people before somebody
takes them out
but if it's an ar-15 they can kill a lot
more people
with decentralizing exponential
technology when that becomes a crispr
gene drive pandemic weapon
and weaponized drones and etc
we just can't have really
disaffected people and that means if i
can get all of my needs met without
interacting with other humans
then either i have to have some top-down
state surveillance system like the china
method
which is already a dystopia
or how do we have access to the level of
technological power people will be
getting
and have us be safe vessels for having
that much technological power
well they have to be no psychologically
really damaged people
and if there are any we have to know the
only way to have that kind of
known that doesn't involve top-down
state surveillance is the kind of
surveillance that a family does
or a tribe does or community does where
my resource provisioning requires
interacting in healthy ways with people
or unlike the kind of asymmetric
surveillance of the state that is just
trying to make sure i'm not a bad guy
it's a symmetric paying attention of
people that actually want to make sure
i'm doing well
so part of the what you're proposing is
a community surveillance
in a way so you're saying basically that
doesn't even have to be developed
because it's
it's an innate function of building
um primate communities that we're
resonating with each other and that
we're realizing if somebody is behaving
kind of outside of the pack then then
that is something to be addressed and is
would you
argue that this is something that is
like an existential
interest of the group because of the
potential so is this like a risk
detection system of a group
does this mean that nobody can be a
hermit no of course it doesn't mean
nobody can be a hermit
but it doesn't mean that in the
presence of
decentralizable catastrophe level
technology
we have to think about some things
differently than we did previously
and the disposition and well-being of
people
matters more to everyone because the
one-to-many capacity of a person is much
much higher
and so the coupling is higher which
means that the care needs to be higher
we're coming back to care again and
again and again so now we're looking at
care as a group phenomenon
so a group caring for the group
and caring for individuals for the sake
of the group
and for the sake of the individual and
for the sake of the individual
so if i'm just translating this to the
health care setting now
where we have a group of people working
together and we have individuals walking
in and out of this setting
and we look at the current
i want to call it epidemic of
suicides in you know among our
colleagues
where are we failing is it have we
become
numb has the system numbed ourselves
have we lost
a sensitivity
you're specifically talking about
suicide amongst doctors
i don't know i haven't studied this um i
would want to really look
at is suicide much
higher amongst doctors than other
professionals of the same pay grade
and other types of similar stress level
um like i'm sure again there's going to
be complex causation that's involved
it's not one thing
we can talk about
why there are kind of
epidemic suicide issues society-wide
um but yeah i wouldn't want to
speak to with doctors without knowing
more
but i think it's pretty easy to see at
least some things
i think it's pretty easy to see that um
the amount of stress doctors go through
even in med school right experiencing
burnout or being on um
some kind of uh
wellbutrin or adderall a ritalin or some
kind of upper just to make it through
school by the time they're just not even
graduating
and then they're supposed to have a
whole career of that and like you
mentioned 72 hour shifts and
i also think that not having a place to
process the emotionality of it
the desensitization of okay so i just
you know was a part of some kids dying
today this experience and
i'm gonna go do it tomorrow and where's
space for that and
um yeah i think i think there's
obviously a lot
of stresses both that are unavoidably
endemic to that
profession that need to be processed in
ways that they aren't currently
processed
and ones that are avoidable by changing
the way the system works
so we could as a group become more
proficient
in detecting the dynamics of the group
and taking care of each other and
we could become more proficient in the
way that we show up as an individual in
the group
and that showing up more proficient
with our peer group with our teams and
with the patient
will help us to
see the patient better see our
colleagues better
and that might create a community that
is kind of mutually supportive
in a way that we are
not so much cluttered by by knowledge
and red tape
but we can actually allow ourselves to
activate
our natural
capacity to care and
and our um i feel like to
to allow ourselves to be authentic in
our natural
state of being and connected that level
yeah i mean it's interesting when you're
talking about the
group care between doctors colleagues
when when someone that we know commit
suicide
it's such a important inquiry
especially if we didn't know they were
close
it's an important inquiry to recognize
that you actually don't know
how close anyone you're talking to ever
is to committing suicide
and you don't know how close to
threshold they are and how your
interaction is going to affect their
relationship to that threshold
and simply being aware of that
changes the importance you put on how
you show up in all the interactions so
much
well we've come a long way in looking
taking a big circle
starting in what does it what does
heart-based medicine mean to you
and uh we're ending on a note of how
important it is to develop a sensitivity
for each other and to be present with
each other
and to know and and how in
in so how many ways this this
finds reflections in our diagnostic
capacity in the way we devise treatments
in the way
we want to create a healthcare system
that uh overcomes the many limitations
that
that we're facing at the moment towards
um
a system where people will feel seen and
heard as human beings rather than being
seen as a disease with with some kind of
background that really doesn't
isn't so important for us thank you
thank you for taking the time being here
thanks for having me thanks for uh
following the call to help this
movement birth we're on it together
thank you thank you this has been a
heart based medicine production
thanks for listening